Guide to the James Weldon Johnson Collection Files
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- "V"
  - Van Dyke, Henry
    - Ladies of the Rachmaninoff Eyes, typescript, carbon and original, signed, first draft, corrected and revised, undated (Box 16, Folder 343)
      With an autograph note signed from the author to Carl (Van Vechten), "Monday, P.M.," accompanying the manuscript, undated.
    - Miss Desdemona, typescript, original, corrected and revised, 1961 (Box 16, Folder 344)
      Inscribed to Carl Van Vechten and dated October 2, 1961.
  - Van Vechten, Carl, 11 typed letters, signed, to Harold Jackman, 1934-1941 (Box 16, Folder 345)
  - Vodery, Will, correspondence and documents, 1944-1952 (Box 17, Folder 346)
    Includes 1 typed letter, signed, from Oscar Hammerstein, dated January 16, 1946. With 1 typed letter, signed, from Robert Milford, on Oscar Hammerstein's stationery, concerning the contractual agreement for Show Boat, dated December 6, 1945.
    A manuscript list made by Hughes and a typed copy signed by him, of materials concerning Will Vodery given by Mrs. Vodery to the James Weldon Johnson Memorial Collection. With miscellaneous song lyrics, royalty statements, and a printed card signed by Hassard Short to Vodery, dated January 13, 1946, New York, with envelope, regarding Show Boat.
    2 autograph postcards to Will Vodery from Bricktop, dated September 22, 1950 and August 7, 1951.
    Gift of Mrs. Rosanne Vodery, 1952.
- "W"
  - Walker, Grace, "To a Tree in November," autograph manuscript, signed, poem of six 3-line stanzas, 1932 (Box 17, Folder 347)
  - Walker, Margaret
    - For My People, setting typescript, original, published: Yale University Press, 1942 (Box 17, Folder 348)
    - Ballad for Nat Turner: Insurrectionist, autograph manuscript, signed, first draft, and typescripts, second and third drafts, signed, 1940, undated (Box 17, Folder 349)
    - "Growing out of the Shadow," essay, typescripts, original, portions of a first draft, second draft, and third draft, with notes and the author's extensive manuscript revisions, before 1943 (Box 17, Folder 350)
      Includes typescript, carbon, final version. Published: Common Ground, 4, no. 1, 1943.
    - "Harriet Tubman," poem, typescript, original, signed, first draft with the author's manuscript revisions and additions, and 1 typed leaf from a later draft, undated (Box 17, Folder 351)
    - "In the Beginning," poem, typescripts, original, drafts, with the author's extensive manuscript revisions, using the title, "Visit to the Psychiatrist", undated (Box 17, Folder 352)
      Includes typescript, original. Final version, complete, with the author's manuscript corrections.
    - Poems, autograph manuscript and typescripts, originals, fragments of several untitled drafts, with the author's manuscript revisions and notes, undated (Box 17, Folder 353)
    - "Sojourner Truth," poem, typescripts, original, signed, with the author's manuscript notes and corrections, undated (Box 17, Folder 354)
    - Untitled poem, typescripts, original, with first line "Some seek their gods in an ancient well...", early drafts, 1943 July 10 (Box 17, Folder 355)
    - "Spirit is Willing," poem, draft, typescript, original, with the author's manuscript revisions, poem of four 4-line stanzas, 1942 December 16 (Box 17, Folder 356)
    - "The Strawberry Man," typescript, carbon, signed, a children's story, 1943 (Box 17, Folder 357)
  - Walker, Mary Kerr, John Gwynee Chaplin, typescript, original, undated (Box 17, Folder 358)
    Includes mounted photographs of John Gwynee Chaplin and his wife, Hannah Gwynne Chaplin.
  - Ward, Theodore, Big White Fog, typescript, carbon, with the author's revisions and a note on the cover in Langston Hughes' hand, 1937, 1938 (Box 17, Folder 359)
  - Warren, S. E., "Altruism," poem, reproduced from typewritten copy, signed, undated (Box 17, Folder 360)
  - Washington, Haines J., poems, typescripts, original, signed, 1930 (Box 17, Folder 361)
    Poems include: "Stuck Up," "Roll 'em an' Weep," "'Pon the dawn," "So Much of Pity," "Think You," "Song for a Banjoe," "Coon Shouting," "Southern Rhapsody." Accompanied by an autograph letter signed from Miss Washington to James Weldon Johnson, December 4, 1930, Long Island, New York, and an autograph note in Mrs. Johnson's hand.
  - Washington, Hazel, "Deep," typescript, original, poem of two 8-line stanzas, undated (Box 17, Folder 362)
  - Watts, A., "The Salen Saga," reproduced from a typewritten copy, signed "A Faulkner (Soonsoitaja) Watts," and inscribed to Langston Hughes, 1953 March (Box 17, Folder 363)
  - Weeks, Ricardo, "To You," autograph manuscript, signed, poem, written to Langston Hughes, on a Christmas card, undated (Box 17, Folder 364)
  - Weld, Theodore D.
    - Garrison, Frank J., 1 autograph letter signed to Garrison, 1881 April 24 (Box 17, Folder 365)
    - Garrison, William Lloyd, 1 autograph letter signed to Garrison, includes letter from Thomas D. Weld to Garrison, 1878 March 16 (Box 17, Folder 366)
    - Marsh, Mr., 1 autograph letter signed to Marsh, 1876 March 19 (Box 17, Folder 367)
    - Weld, Mr., 1 autograph letter signed to his brother, 1865 July 24 (Box 17, Folder 368)
  - Welles, Gideon
    - Welles, Robert G., 1 autograph letter signed to Welles, 1863 October 16 (Box 17, Folder 369)
    - Welles, Samuel, 3 autograph letters signed to his father, 1819-20 (Box 17, Folder 370)
    - Unidentified correspondent, 1 autograph letter signed to unidentified correspondent, Washington, 1847 September 13 (Box 17, Folder 371)
  - Wheatley, Phillis, inscriptions to Thomas Walcott, March 26, 1774, xerox made from recto and verso of title leaf, John Lathrop's The Importance of Early Piety (Boston, 1771), undated (Box 17, Folder 372)
  - Wheeler, Bill
    - "Black Bitters," typescript, original, signed, with the author's manuscript corrections and note, an account of a combat mission, undated (Box 17, Folder 373)
    - Essays, typescripts, carbon, contents include "Black Justice" and "Confession: (While Overseas)", undated (Box 17, Folder 374)
    - Poems, typescripts, original and carbon, undated (Box 17, Folder 375)
      Poems include "Almost Sedition," "Boomerang!" "Challenge," "Cinema Sam," "Compensation," "Eve of Love," "Facin' Facts," "The Hour Glass," "Oran Incident," "Outnumbered," "The Pay Off," "Revelation," "Scapegoat," "Speculatin'," "Travelin'."
  - Wheeler, Charles Enoch, Prelude, drafts of poems, autograph manuscript, signed, 1943 (Box 17, Folder 376)
    Poems include "Dedication poem (For Johnnie)," "Bronze," "Old Griefs," "Soliloquy," "Paths," "Moon Song," "Volcano," "Prelude," "Effigy," "Beyond All Tears," "Bitterness," "Your Eyes," "Tumult," "Melancholia," "Hate," "Space," "Longing," "Desolation," "Myth," "Interlude," "Lament," "Chamber," "Lute," "Reliquial," "These Lines." Published: Cleveland, Press of Flozari, Pegasus Studios, 1943.
    Gift of the author through Carl Van Vechten.
  - White, Carl Darrow
    - Think It Over, George, typescript, carbon, signed, undated (Box 17, Folder 377)
    - ---, typescript, carbon, signed, corrected, undated (Box 17, Folder 378)
  - White, Walter, 2 typed letters, signed, to Harold Jackman, 1939-1940 (Box 17, Folder 379)
  - Whiteman, Maxwell, A Century of Fiction by American Negroes, 1853-1952, typescript, carbon, signed, with the author's manuscript note, "A descriptive bibliography", 1955 (Box 17, Folder 380)
  - Wilberforce, Samuel, 1 autograph letter, signed, to Frances H. Spragge, 1842 July 8 (Box 17, Folder 381)
  - Wiley, Bill Irwin, Southern Negroes: 1861-1865, setting typescript, original, with the author's manuscript corrections and with publisher's editorial markings, published: New Haven, Yale University Press, 1938 (Yale Historical Publications Miscellany, XXXI) (Box 18, Folder 382)
  - Wiley, Stella, date book, autograph manuscript, performance engagements of Miss Wiley (and Russell Brandon), 1903-1904 (Box 18, Folder 383)
  - Wilkins, Thelma L., "Onward," poem, typescript, original, 1934 January 26 (Box 18, Folder 384)
  - Williams, Clarence, untitled poem, typescript, carbon, the first line of which reads "Michigan waters ain't like sherry wine /...", undated (Box 18, Folder 385)
    Typescript made by Carl Van Vechten, with ink corrections and a note by him, and pencil annotations in an unidentified hand. Lyrics by Williams, recorded by Lena Wilson on the album, "Michigan Water Blues."
  - Williams, Egbert Austin, The Start, autograph manuscript, red leather notebook, a description of a journey, unfinished, with two leaves of accounts, undated (Box 18, Folder 386)
  - Williams, George W., 1 autograph letter, signed, to the New York Globe, 1883 (Box 18, Folder 387)
  - Williams, Vincent, After a Lynch-Tree Harvest, typescript, original, "a play-poem", undated (Box 18, Folder 388)
  - Willkie, Wendell L.
    - Address at the 23rd Annual Conference of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, Los Angeles, California, reproduced from typewritten copy, signed., 1942 July 20 (Box 18, Folder 389)
    - Opening remarks of Wendell L. Willkie, as chairman of the inaugural dinner of Freedom House, Commodore Hotel, New York, New York, reproduced from typewritten copy, signed. Inscribed by the author to the James Weldon Johnson Memorial Collection., 1942 March 19 (Box 18, Folder 390)
      Typed letter, signed, from Walter White to Carl Van Vechten, 1942 March 31, removed to the Carl Van Vechten Papers.
  - Winks, Robin, research materials for The Blacks in Canada, typescript, xerox copy, 1974 (Box 18, Folder 391)
    Inventory prepared by the Schomburg Collection of photocopies presented by Winks. With an autograph note signed from Winks to Donald Gallup, February 4, 1974, New Haven, Connecticut, accompanying the manuscript.
    Gift of the author, February 1974.
  - Winn, Edward H., notebook, autograph manuscript, signed, undated (Box 18, Folder 392)
    From the personal collection of James Weldon Johnson.
    Contains routes for three seasons with Isham's Octaroons (probably late 1890s), also skeletons of several jobs.
  - Woodson, Carter G., 2 typed letters, signed, to Rosetta Gaston, 1945, 1950 (Box 18, Folder 393)
  - Worthy, William, "The 'Scholarly' F.B.I.," typescript, carbon, article on investigations by the F.B.I. into libraries specializing in Black American collections, undated (Box 18, Folder 394)
    Gift of the author, 1954.
  - Wright, Richard, 1 typed letter, signed, to Harold Jackman, 1938 April 13 (Box 18, Folder 395)